We've created a dataset, and we've created and edited some members within a dataset.
我們已經建立了一個資料集，並且在資料集中建立和編輯了一些成員。
Now let's learn a little more about working with datasets.
現在讓我們進一步了解如何操作資料集。
Just a reminder, some of these handy commands.
提醒您幾個實用指令。
When you type save, that saves the dataset, and it remains in edit mode.
輸入 save 指令會儲存資料集，並保持在編輯模式。
And when you press F3, that saves the data and returns you to the previous panel.
按下 F3 鍵會儲存資料並回到前一個畫面。
So if you're all done editing and you want to exit and save, just hit F3.
如果編輯完成，想要儲存並離開，只要按 F3。
If you've made a bunch of edits that you're not entirely sure about,
如果你做了很多修改，且不太確定是否要保留，
and you want to exit without committing any of them, enter cancel or can for short.
想要不保存直接離開，輸入 cancel 或簡寫 can。
If it's configured for quit, you can also press F12.
若設定為 quit，也可按 F12。
One command you'll probably use a lot when working on datasets is the find command.
處理資料集時，你可能會經常用到 find 指令。
Find is abbreviated as F for find.
Find 縮寫為 F，表示尋找。
Then after F, place your search string.
接著在 F 後面輸入您的搜尋字串。
On this screen, we're trying to find the word back.
在這個畫面中，我們嘗試尋找單字 back。
So we're typing F space back into the command line.
所以我們在指令列輸入 F 空格 back。
If there are multiple occurrences of the word, you can press F5 to advance to the next one.
如果該字出現多次，您可按 F5 跳到下一個。
The highlight command, spelled H-I-L-I-T-E,
highlight 命令，拼作 H-I-L-I-T-E，
lets us tell the editor to set the colors and language sensitive editing features for a specific format.
讓編輯器設定特定格式的顏色與語言感知編輯功能。
When you type highlight and hit enter, we get this menu of languages, coloring, and options.
輸入 highlight 並按 Enter，會出現這個語言、著色和選項的選單。
Here we can select our programming language, set the coloring mode, and select a few of those options.
我們可選編程語言、設定著色模式，並挑選部分選項。
We select an option with a forward slash.
用斜線來選擇一個選項。
So if we select the option for highlight find strings, and then we press F3 to get back to the editor,
如果我們選擇突出顯示搜尋字串選項，然後按 F3 回到編輯器，
notice that the F back command highlights the instances of back in the editor.
會注意到 F back 指令會在編輯器中標示出 back 的所有出現位置。
By the way, if you know the language you want a format for, you can type it out in the command line,
順帶一提，如果你知道想要的語言格式，可以直接在指令列輸入，
like highlight JCL, and that will color the screen specifically for JCL.
例如 highlight JCL，畫面就會專門為 JCL 上色。
A couple of quick notes on this.
關於這點有幾個快速說明。
Some of the highlight formatting options need to be enabled by the installer or person who maintains your ISPF installation.
某些突出顯示格式選項需要由安裝者或維護你 ISPF 安裝的人啟用。
So if you're on a different system and things look a little bit different, that could be why.
所以如果你在不同系統而畫面看起來有點不同，可能就是這個原因。
Also, these options are only available in the edit mode.
而且這些選項只有在編輯模式下可用。
If you're browsing a file, you won't see these colors.
如果你只是瀏覽檔案，就不會看到這些顏色。
A lot of times when something doesn't work right, you get an error, and the message might say,
很多時候當某些功能出錯時，你會看到錯誤訊息，上面可能會寫著，
error detected at line 50, column 42, or something like that.
在第50行，第42欄偵測到錯誤，或類似的情況。
And we can easily see what line we're at because we have the numbers on the left side of the screen there,
我們可以很容易看到目前所在行數，因為畫面左側有行號。
but what about that error at column 42?
但那第42欄的錯誤呢？
Are we supposed to sit there and count out one, two, three, four, five?
我們要坐著數一、二、三、四、五嗎？
Of course not.
當然不用。
You can bring up a column guide, and you can actually do this one of two ways.
你可以叫出欄位指示器，其實有兩種方式能做到。
Type calls, C-O-L-S, up in the command line area, and you get a little ruler that pops up,
在指令行輸入 calls，C-O-L-S，就會跳出一把直尺，
and it will always be there at the top of your screen for you.
它會固定出現在畫面頂端，非常方便。
That's pretty handy, but what if I really only want to show a column guide for one line?
這很實用，但如果我只想顯示某行的欄位指示器怎麼辦？
Type calls, C-O-L-S, over the line number you want the column guide for,
在要顯示欄位指示器的行號上輸入 calls，C-O-L-S，
and it will insert one in the editor right above it.
它會在編輯器中於上方插入一行。
Now, this does not show up in the actual data set.
這不會顯示在實際的資料集裡。
You'll notice it doesn't have a record number over there, but as you scroll up and down, it moves with the data.
你會注意到那邊沒有記錄號碼，但上下滾動時，它會隨資料一起移動。
So two styles of creating column guides, and those will definitely come in handy.
兩種建立欄位導引的方式，都非常實用。
We looked at find, and we also have a change command.
我們看過 find，也有 change 指令。
This can be used to replace a string of characters with another,
它可以用來將一串字元替換成另一串，
like if we wanted to change all instances of one, two, three, four with five, six, seven, eight.
例如把所有一、二、三、四都改成五、六、七、八。
To use the change command, just enter change, followed by what you want to change.
使用 change 指令，只要輸入 change，接著是你要改的內容。
Followed by what you want to change it with.
再接著是你想改成的內容。
If you want to change all instances, follow that with all, otherwise it will only change the next one.
如果想替換全部，後面加上 all，否則只會改下一個。
And there's a whole lot of options you can use for the change command, but for now, we're just going to keep it simple.
change 指令有很多選項，但現在我們先保持簡單。
Up next is the bounds command.
接下來是 bounds 指令。
This comes in handy from time to time.
這個指令偶爾會很有用。
Let's say we want to issue a change command, but we only want to change data located between the first and 25th column.
假設我們想執行 change 指令，但只改變第 1 到第 25 欄的資料。
Sounds tricky, but with the bounds command, we can type bounds space one, space 25,
聽起來很複雜，但用 bounds 指令，輸入 bounds 一空格 1 一空格 25，
and now our change command is limited to the area in the first 25 columns.
就能將 change 指令限制在前 25 欄的範圍內。
To set it back, just type bounds with nothing after it and hit enter, and it will go back to default.
要復原設定，只輸入 bounds 後按 Enter，就會回到預設。
Say you want to copy or move an entire data set somewhere else.
假如你想複製或移動整個資料集到別處，
One way of doing this is with the move copy utility, and I'm going to show you a shortcut of how to get there.
其中一個方法是用 move copy 工具，我會示範快速進入的方法。
It's in the utility section, which is option three, and within there, move copy utility is option number three.
它在工具功能表的第 3 選項，裡面 move copy 工具是第 3 選項。
Since we know this, we can get there by going to 3.3.
既然我們知道這點，就可以直接前往 3.3。
It'll jump us directly there without needing to stop at the screen in between.
它將直接帶我們到那裡，不需要停留在中間畫面。
So from the main screen, we're going to type 3.3, and that puts us at the move copy utility.
從主畫面，我們輸入 3.3，就會進入 move copy 工具。
And we can actually jump directly from any panel to any other panel by putting an equals in front of that.
其實我們可以在任何面板前加上等號，直接跳到任何其他面板。
So equals 3.3 or whatever in the command line.
例如在指令列輸入 =3.3 或其他。
So no need to go back to that main panel.
這樣就不需要回到主面板。
That should save us quite a bit of time.
這可以為我們節省不少時間。
All right, moving and copying.
好的，開始移動與複製。
Put either an M or a C for move or copy on the command line.
在指令列輸入 M 或 C，代表移動或複製。
Then either use the project group type fields to specify your data set or type out the name of the data set on the name line.
接著用 project group type 欄位指定資料集， 或直接在名稱列輸入資料集名稱。
Note that you can use the member field to specify a single member, or you can use an asterisk or splat to specify all members.
請注意，您可以使用 member 欄位指定單一成員，或使用星號（*）指定所有成員。
You can also use a pattern like L splat to tell it only members that start with an L.
您也可以使用像 L* 的模式，只選擇以 L 開頭的成員。
Hit enter, and then the next screen will come up.
按 Enter，接著會出現下一個畫面。
Fill out the name of the target data set, where it's going, and hit enter.
填寫目標資料集的名稱和位置，然後按 Enter。
And the copy or move will begin.
接著複製或移動作業就會開始。
Renaming a data set is fairly similar.
重新命名資料集的方式相當類似。
Using option 3.2, the data set utility panel, enter the old data set name and specify an R on the command line.
使用選項 3.2，進入資料集工具面板，輸入舊資料集名稱並在指令列指定 R。
The next screen will prompt you for the new name.
下一個畫面會提示您輸入新名稱。
Hit enter, and there you go.
按 Enter，完成操作。
If you want to rename a member, not the entire data set, use option 3.1 for library utilities.
如果要重新命名成員而非整個資料集，請使用選項 3.1 的資料庫工具。
Fill out all these fields or fully spell out the name of the member in the other partitioned or sequential data set field.
請填寫所有欄位，或在另一個分割或序列資料集中完全拼出成員名稱。
And just follow the prompts, which by now should seem pretty familiar.
照著提示操作，現在應該已經相當熟悉了。
Deleting data set members, that's also done in 3.1.
刪除資料集成員，也是在3.1完成。
Just use the command D for delete.
只要使用命令D代表刪除。
Depending on how your ISPF is configured, it may or may not ask you if you're sure you want to delete those members.
根據你的 ISPF 設定，可能會或不會詢問你確定要刪除這些成員。
Hey, better safe than sorry.
多一份小心總比後悔好。
One more thing, we looked at the data set list utility earlier, which can be found at option 3.4.
還有一件事，我們之前看過資料集清單工具，它在3.4選項。
And we saw how you can get a listing of the members of a data set by typing out a qualifier or series of qualifiers into the dsnamelevel field and hitting enter.
看到你可以在 dsnamelevel 欄位輸入一個或多個限定字並按下Enter， 取得資料集成員清單。
Now, check this out. When the listing comes up, we can not only edit and view the members from here by placing an E or a V into the command area,
看看這個，清單顯示後，我們不只可以輸入 E 或 V 來編輯或檢視成員，
but we can also rename them with an R.
還可以用 R 來重新命名。
Delete with a D, copy with a C-O, move with an M-O, and more.
用 D 刪除，C-O 複製，M-O 移動，還有更多。
A fuller listing of these commands is in a file attached to this lesson.
更完整的命令列表在本課程附帶的檔案中。
So that's that. You've learned how to create and manage data sets and members.
就是這樣。你已學會如何建立和管理資料集及成員。
You're ready to take on the world of data sets, at least.
至少你已準備好迎接資料集的世界。